We were talking about options API and the bridge over the composition API, and then we
went ahead and basically showed you what it was like to only use composition API where
we'd move everything into the setup function. But I did promise you that all that
boilerplate we were writing, well there is a grass screen on the other side and it truly
is because something that came out recently with view 3.2 and above is the concept of
script setup. And so before we dive into code, I'm going to do some slides just to give you
just like a basic overview so that it helps to hopefully explain things a little bit better.
So here we have a view component. As you can see here we have our script and then as we can see here
we're using the options API to actually set everything out with composition API. So your setup life
cycle hook. We can see that this is a standard counter app with a count of rough 0. We have a computer
property for example. We have a method to increment the count and we return everything in the object.
Fairly standard from the composition API perspective. Well one of the things we realize though
is that this is still a lot of boilerplate considering that a lot of people are opting into composition
API for certain components in a pure fashion. So how might we make this better? Well first thing
first, we went ahead and we're going to say we're going to assume the entire script block is
going to be a setup life cycle hook. So that's why you see we moved the setup setup, actually we moved
it all the way up into that script block. So now script has this attribute of setup which tells
the compiler hey we are now in pure setup life cycle hook function. So what does that mean?
Let me get rid of an export default object because we're going to do some compiler optimizations
that we can assume based on the fact that we're only working in script setup. Then on top of that
because we can now do some basically view can do some magic as far as detecting what's being used
in the template and whatnot we can actually get rid of the return object entirely.
And so at the end of the day, this code works exactly the same as everything else that you saw earlier.
Okay, so let's go ahead and see that in action shall we? So what we're going to do is we're going
to take the restaurant page that we've been working with and we're going to trim that down
into the script setup format. So first thing first, we're going to add the setup attribute here and
what you notice that immediately is that basically it starts to say hey a lot of these things
you're talking about they're not being used. So for example we can get rid of this defined component.
So that can just get deleted. So let me go ahead on the bottom because now the whole thing is
is script setup we don't need we don't have the options API anymore. So this helper method goes away
and then because the components are automatically being registered on import we don't need to manually
register them either. So there's going bye bye. And then here we don't need to set up here why
because well we already have the setup attribute being defined up here in the script block and then
by scroll all the way down there's the other one and then finally we can delete all this return stuff
and then that's it. Do you now have your script setup block and everything still leverages view
the way you want it to but it's basically more of that vanilla JavaScript land and then sprinkling
any helper methods where it makes sense. And so now that I've done that and shown you how that works
we're going to have you have a quick try at that. So given that this is mainly just kind of like
refactoring exercise we're just going to give it five minutes just for people with the practice doing this
and so let me go ahead and actually set this up real quick. Okay so now if you click if you check out
the O4 exercise branch that will let you go ahead and like we said on your dishes page you're
going to do the same exact thing where we're going to strip away all the boiler plate and get
you down into that script setup block. So hopefully that was mostly an effort in stripping
that component. So we're just going to do this real quick together. So once again first thing
do we want to use the script setup block add the setup attribute then we can go ahead and delete
this export line. We can delete the components line. We don't need setup anymore. I'll deal with
that in a little bit. We don't need any of this return block. We don't need any of this at the bottom.
I think we save. We're mostly there. Just need to eliminate this and that's it.
They and now you have your script setup block and it looks great. And so going forward for the
rest of this workshop we're going to basically use the script setup block syntax. And so now you've
seen that journey and so hopefully everyone can follow along from this point on.